Finding Aid for E. Hardy Luther papers, 1945-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
E. Hardy Luther papers 1945-1982
Luther, E. Hardy, 1898-1982.
1 linear foot
85275 Aa 2
Executive and historian of Consumers Power Company of Michigan. Correspondence, speeches, articles, and copy of his history of the company entitled, "Song of Service; A Century of Consumers Power Company and Its Predecessors"; also include articles on history of Jackson County, Michigan; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of E. W. Luther (donor no. 2181 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
E. Hardy Luther was born on August 25, 1898 in Grand Rapids, Michigan. After graduation from Jackson High School and the University of Michigan, Luther joined Consumers Power Company in 1921. He served as an assistant to the Division Manager of Pontiac from 1926 to 1943, at which time he was transferred to Kalamazoo. In 1951 Luther was promoted to General Training and Educational Supervisor, and in 1956 to General Personnel Development Supervisor.
In the 1940s, Luther became interested in the history of Consumers Power and began recording the recollections of past company employees. The result of his efforts was a company history entitled, "Song of Service: A Century of Consumers Power Company and Its Predecessors, 1856-1956." Luther also maintained an interest in the local history of Jackson and Kalamazoo. He wrote a history of St. Paul's Church in Jackson, and, as a member of the Jackson County Historical Society, gave numerous lectures on Jackson history and the history of electrical power in Michigan.
Luther died in 1982.
The papers of E. Hardy Luther reflect his life-long interest in Consumers Power and the local history of Jackson County. Luther's history of Consumer's Power, "Song of Service," comprises the bulk of the collection. The several inches of Luther's personal papers include correspondence, speeches, interviews, and unpublished articles relative to the development of electrical power in Michigan, management techniques of Consumers Power and the history of the Jackson Community in the 19th century.
Subjects:
Consumers Power Company.; Electric industries.; Jackson County (Mich.)--History.; Luther, E. Hardy, 1898-1982.; Public utilities--Michigan.; Song of service.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Au Sable River (Mich.); Business enterprises--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Consumers Power Company.; Fishing--Michigan--Au Sable River.; Kalamazoo (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Wanigans.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Consumer's Power / Jackson County
  - Correspondence, 1945-1979 (Box 1)
  - Jackson County High School Alumni correspondence and programs, 1952-1972 (Box 1)
  - Speeches and Interviews re: Michigan History and Business Management, 1951-1970s (Box 1)
  - Articles (unpublished) on Michigan History, ca. 1950-1982 (Box 1)
  - Jackson County Historical Associations articles and honorary Material, 1975-1982 (Box 1)
  - Consumers Power Company history
    - Speeches and Unpublished Articles, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - "Song of Service: A History of Consumers Power Company, 1856-1956", 4 volumes (Box 1)
  - Photographs, ca. 1912 of Consumers Power Company employees and investors camping and traveling by wanigan on the Au Sable River; also copy print photographs of the Kalamazoo, Michigan business district, ca. 1856 and 1875 (Box 1)